<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be ministred, enquired of, and answered in the visitation of the Right Worshipfull Iames Hussey, doctor of the ciuill law and commissarie generall to the Most Reuerend Father in God the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury his grace within the citie and diocesse of Cant.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Canterbury.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10161.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22884830</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22884830</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1777:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be ministred, enquired of, and answered in the visitation of the Right Worshipfull Iames Hussey, doctor of the ciuill law and commissarie generall to the Most Reuerend Father in God the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury his grace within the citie and diocesse of Cant.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Canterbury.</author>
                  <author>Hussey, James.</author>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1611-1633 : Abbot)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Eliot's Court Press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Name of publisher and date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B².</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Exeter College (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES To be miniſtred, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of, and anſwered in the <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the right Worſhipfull</hi> IAMES HVSSEY Doctor of the Ciuill Law and Commiſſarie generall to the moſt reuerend Father in God the Lord Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury his Grace within the Citie and Dioceſſe of <hi>Cant.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:25860:2"/>
            <head>The tenour of the Oath to be <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to the Church-wardens and Sworne-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that all affection, fauour, hatred, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or malice ſet aſide, you ſhall vpon due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Articles giuen you in charge, preſent all and euery ſuch perſon of, or within your Pariſh, as hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any offence mentioned in theſe or any of theſe Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected, and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of any ſuch offence: wherein you ſhall diſcharge your conſciences vprightly, and according to truth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of malice, preſenting any contrary to truth, nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent any, and ſo conceale the truth, hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine truth, and to ſuppreſſe vice: So helpe you God, and by the contents of this Booke.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:25860:2"/>
            <head>THE ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Booke of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</note> Whether haue you in your ſeuerall Churches and Chappels the booke of Conſtitutions or Canons Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, ready to be read by your Miniſter, according to his Maieſties pleaſure, publiſhed by his Highneſſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, vnder the great Seale of England: and whether hath your Miniſter read the ſame, or any part thereof vpon Sundayes and Holydayes in the afternoone before diuine Seruice accordingly, yea or not?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Item,
<note place="margin">Articles of Religion.</note> whether is there any in your Pariſh that doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne any of the Articles of Religion, agréed vpon in <hi>Anno 1562.</hi> and eſtabliſhed in the Church of England?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Item,
<note place="margin">Pray for the King, &amp;c.</note> whether doth your Miniſter vſe to pray for the Kings Maieſtie, King <hi>Iames, Frederick</hi> the Prince Elector Palatine, with the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife, and all their royall Progenie, with addition of ſuch ſtile and Titles as are due and appertaining to his Maieſtie, and exhort the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to obedience to his Highneſſe, &amp; other Magiſtrates being in authoritie vnder him?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Item, whether is there any in your Pariſh,
<note place="margin">Impugne the Rites or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</note> that impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth or ſpeaketh againſt the Rites and Ceremonies eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Church of England, or the lawfull vſe of them? you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Item,
<note place="margin">Impugne the Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> are there any in your Pariſh that do impugne the gouernment of the Church of England, vnder the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and the reſt that beare office in the ſame; affirming that the ſame is Antichriſtian, or repugnant to the word of God?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Item,
<note place="margin">Prophaning the Sabboth.</note> whether any perſons haue lurked and tippled in Tauernes or Ale-houſes on Sundayes or other Holidayes, or vſed his or their manuall craft or trade vpon the ſaid daies, or otherwiſe prophaned them, or any of them, in any ſort, and
<pb facs="tcp:25860:3"/>eſpecially in the time of Diuine Seruice.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Item,
<note place="margin">Preſcript forme of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice.</note> whether is the preſcript forme of diuine Seruice vſed by your Miniſter vpon Sundayes and Holidayes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the booke of Common Prayer: and whether doth your Miniſter onely obſerue all the orders, rites and ceremonies preſcribed in the ſaid booke of Common Prayer, as well in reading publike prayers, the Letanie, as alſo in adminiſtring the Sacraments in ſuch manner and forme as in the booke of Common Prayer is inioyned?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Item,
<note place="margin">Bravvling in Church or Church-yard.</note> whether hath any perſon in your pariſh quarrelled or ſtricken, or vſed any violence vnto, or with your Miniſter, or any other in the Church or Church-yard, or vſed himſelfe diſorderly in the Church by filthy and prophane talke, or any other rude and immodeſt behauiour?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Item,
<note place="margin">Reuerence in time of diuine Seruice.</note> whether is that due reuerence and humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion vſed within your Church or Chapell in the time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice, as by the eightéenth Conſtitution is preſcribed: whether each one in the Church or Chappell do apply &amp; order himſelfe there, in time of diuine Seruice, as by the latter part of the ſame Conſtitution is moſt commendably inioyned?</p>
            <p n="10">10 Item,
<note place="margin">Bread and vvine at the Communion.</note> whether the Church wardens do prouide againſt euery Communion, with the aduice of the Miniſter, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantitie of fine white bread, and of good and wholeſome wine for the number of the communicants that ſhall receiue, and that to be brought in a cleane and ſweets ſtanding pot of pewter, or of other pure mettall?</p>
            <p n="11">11 Item,
<note place="margin">Miniſtring &amp; receiuing of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> whether doth your Miniſter adminiſter the holy Communion ſo often, and at ſuch time, as that euery pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner may receiue the ſame at leaſt thrice in euery yéere, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of once at Eaſter, as by the booke of Common Prayer is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: and whether doth your Miniſter receiue the ſame himſelf on euery day, before that he adminiſtreth it to others, and vſe the words of the inſtitution according to the booke at euery time that the bread or wine is renued, in ſuch manner &amp; forme, as by the prouiſo of the 21. Canon is directed, or wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is faultie: and whether is warning giuen by him before hand for the Communion, as the 22. Canon requireth?</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether doth your Miniſter adminiſter the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to any that doth not humbly knéele at the receiuing of
<pb facs="tcp:25860:3"/>the ſame? what are the names of them that refuſe to kneele at the receiuing thereof?</p>
            <p n="13">13 Item,
<note place="margin">Offenders not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note> whether hath your Miniſter admitted any noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious offenders or ſchiſmaticks to the Communion, contrary to the 26 and 27. Conſtitutions?</p>
            <p n="14">14 Item, whether the Miniſter,
<note place="margin">No ſtrangers to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> togither with the Church-wardens and Queſt men, do take diligent heede and care, not onely that all and euery your owne pariſhioners doe receiue thrice in euery yéere, as aforeſaid, but alſo that no ſtrangers of any other pariſh doe come often and commonly to your Church from their owne pariſh Church: and you are now to preſent the names of all thoſe, who being 16 yeares of age or vpwardes, haue not in their owne pariſh receiued the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at or ſince Eaſter laſt?</p>
            <p n="15">15 Item,
<note place="margin">Signe of the Croſſe.</note> whether doth your Miniſter vſe to ſigne the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with the ſigne of the croſſe when they are baptized, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the booke of Common prayer:
<note place="margin">Refuſe to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize.</note> and whether he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, or wilfully refuſed to baptize any infant in his pariſh being in danger, hauing beene dulie informed of the weaknes thereof: and whether the childe hath died in his default with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out baptiſme; or whether hath he at any time refuſed or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to burie the dead, or to miniſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to any being in extremitie of ſickneſſe, hauing béene required thereunto?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Item,
<note place="margin">Reſidencie.</note> whether is your Miniſter continually reſident with you vpon his Benefice, or for how long time hath he bin abſent: and where is he reſident for the moſt part, and what other Benefice hath he?</p>
            <p n="17">17 Item, whether doth your Miniſter preach vſually,
<note place="margin">Preaching ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Canons.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Conſtitutions, either in his owne cure with you, or elſe in ſome other church or chappell néere adioyning, wherein no Preacher is: or how oft hath he béene negligent in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Item,
<note place="margin">More Cures than one.</note> whether doth your Miniſter or Curate ſerue any more Cures than one: if yea, then what other cure doth hee ſerue?</p>
            <p n="19">19 Item, if your Miniſter be not licenſed to preach,
<note place="margin">Licenſed to preach.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he take vpon him to expound the Scriptures, either in his owne cure, or elſe-where?</p>
            <p n="20">
               <pb facs="tcp:25860:4"/> 20 Item,
<note place="margin">None to preach but licenſed.</note> whether hath any perſon bin admitted to preach within your church or chappell, but ſuch as you haue well knowne to be ſufficiently licenſed?</p>
            <p n="21">21 Item,
<note place="margin">Preachers to read Seruice, &amp;c twice a yeere.</note> whether doth your Lecturer and Preacher, your Parſon or Vicar, read diuine ſeruice, and adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in his owne perſon, twice euery yéere, obſeruing all the ceremonies in the Booke of common prayer eſtabliſhed?</p>
            <p n="22">22 Item,
<note place="margin">Not to refuſe the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion becauſe the Miniſter is no Preacher.</note> is there any in your Pariſh that refuſe to haue their children baptized, or themſelues to receiue the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at the hands of your Miniſter, becauſe he is no preacher? you ſhall preſent their names. And if your Miniſter, ſithence the publiſhing of the ſaid booke of Canons, hath receiued any ſuch perſons (being not of his owne cure) to the communion, or baptized any of their children, you ſhall likewiſe preſent him.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Item, whether are there any priuate meetings, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, or conuenticles, either by day or by night, vſed or had within the Pariſh by any Miniſter, or Miniſters, or any Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſons tending to faction and ſchiſme? Declare the parties names, the places where, the times when, and how often haue you knowne any ſuch meetings, aſſemblies, or conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Item,
<note place="margin">Surplice, Hood, &amp;c.</note> whether doth your Miniſter weare the Surplice whileſt he is ſaying the publike prayers, and miniſtring the Sacraments: and if he be any Graduate, whether then doth he alſo weare vpon his Surprice, during the times aforeſaid, ſuch a hood as by the order of his Vniuerſitie is agreeable to his degree?</p>
            <p n="25">25 Item,
<note place="margin">Catechiſme.</note> whether doth your Miniſter on euery Sunday &amp; Holiday before Euening prayer, for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of his Pariſh, in the ten Commandements, Articles of Beleefe, and in the Lords Prayer, as alſo in the Catechiſme, ſet forth in the Booke of common Prayer, and whether doe all Fathers, Mothers, Maſters and Miſtreſſes, cauſe their children, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and apprentiſes, to come thither to heare, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and taught therein: and thoſe that do not their duties herein, you ſhalt preſent their names?</p>
            <p n="26">26 Item,
<note place="margin">Vnlavvfull marriage.</note> whether hath your Miniſter, without licenſe from
<pb facs="tcp:25860:4"/>the Arch-biſhop, the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, ſolemnized marriage betwixt any parties, the banes not being thrée ſeuerall Sundaies or Holidaies firſt publiſhed in time of diuine Seruice, in the ſeuerall churches or chappels of their ſeuerall abode, according to the Booke of Common Prayer, and that alſo betwixt the houres of eight and twelue in the forenoone: and furthermore, whether hath your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſince the laſt Canons publiſhed, ſolemnized any marriage betwixt any perſons, being vnder the age of one and twentie yéeres, although the hanes be thrice aſked, before ſuch time as the parents haue made knowne vnto him their conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: and whether hath he married any of another Dioceſſe, who are they, and by what authoritie, and when?</p>
            <p n="27">27 Item,
<note place="margin">Bid holidayes and faſting-dayes.</note> whether your Miniſter doe euery Sunday bid Holidaies, and faſting dayes, as by the Booke of Common Prayer is appointed?</p>
            <p n="28">28 Item, whether doth your Miniſter euery ſixe moneths,
<note place="margin">Denounce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate perſons.</note> denounce in his Pariſh all ſuch of his Pariſh as doe perſeuere in the ſentence of excommunication, not ſeeking to be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? and whether hath he admitted into the Church any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon excommunicate, without a certificate of his abſolution from the Ordinarie, or his Subſtitute?</p>
            <p n="29">29 Item, whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate,
<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated perſons not to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at publike prayer in the Church.</note> hath ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated and ſaid diuine Seruice and prayers in the Church, when any perſon that he knew to be excommunicated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced for an excommunicate perſon, was preſent in the ſame Church at that time among the Congregation: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath ſuffered any excommunicate perſon (being a member cut off from the Church and from Chriſtian ſocietie) to be partaker of thoſe prayers, and hath not commanded the Church wardens of the pariſh, or ſome other, to put him out of the Church, or otherwiſe ceaſed from ſaying any diuine prayers during the time of the preſence of ſuch excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſon thereat, and preſent: who hath offended herein, and how often?</p>
            <p n="30">30 Item, whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate,
<note place="margin">Staying the publiſhing of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions.</note> of any your churches or chappels, hauing receiued any excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſuſpenſion or aggrauation from his Ordinary, or his Subſtitute, againſt any of their pariſhioners, haue preſumed
<pb facs="tcp:25860:5"/>to make ſtay of, and not publiſhed ſuch excommunication, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion or aggrauation, according to the tenor thereof, the next Sunday or Holiday after the receit of the ſame in your church or chappell at the time of diuine Seruice: if any bee faultie herein, preſent their names, and how oft default hath béene made in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="31">31 Item,
<note place="margin">Viſit the ſicke.</note> whether is your Miniſter painfull in viſiting the ſicke, according to the Booke of Common Prayer?</p>
            <p n="32">32 Item,
<note place="margin">Fauourer of Recuſants.</note> whether is your Parſon, Vicar or Curats: ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to frequent, or to be ouer-conuerſant with, or a fauourer of Recuſants, whereby he is ſuſpected not to be ſincere in Religion?</p>
            <p n="33">33 Item,
<note place="margin">Lay perſons executing the office of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the Church.</note> hath any preſumed to execute the office of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Deacon in any your Churches, and to ſay and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the diuine Seruice there, or to ſerue the Cure of your Pariſh, not being a Miniſter or Deacon: and whether any Deacon hath preſumed to miniſter the Sacraments in any your Churches, not hauing firſt receiued the full Orders of Prieſthood: if yea, preſent what his name is, where he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth; and how often he hath offended herein.</p>
            <p n="34">34 Item,
<note place="margin">Regiſter book.</note> whether is there in your church or chappell one parchment Regiſter Booke prouided for Chriſtnings, Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Burials: and whether is the ſame duely and exactly kept according to the Conſtitutions in that behalfe prouided?</p>
            <p n="35">35 Item,
<note place="margin">Decencie in apparell.</note> whether doth your Miniſter vſe ſuch decencie and comelineſſe in his apparell, as by the 74. Conſtitution is enioyned?</p>
            <p n="36">36 Item,
<note place="margin">Schoolmaſter</note> doth any take vpon him to teach Schoole in your pariſh without ſpeciall licence of his Ordinarie: and whether doth your Schoolemaſter bring his ſchollers to the Church to heare Diuine Seruice and Sermons: and whether doth he inſtruct them in the Catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="37">37 Item,
<note place="margin">Book of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, and things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Church.</note> whether haue you prouided the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and the Bible of the new Tranſlation lately ſet forth by his Maieſties authoritie, and the booke of Homilies: and whether haue you in your Church or Chappell a Font of ſtone ſet vp in the ancient vſuall place, a conuenient &amp; decent Communion Table, with a carpet of ſilke, or ſome other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſtuffe, and a faire linnen cloth to lay thereon at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb facs="tcp:25860:5"/>time: and whether is the ſame Table then placed in ſuch conuenient ſort within the Chancell or Church, as that the miniſter may be beſt heard in his prayer and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that the greater number may communicate: and whether are the Ten Commandements ſet vpon the Eaſt end of your Church or Chappell, where the people may beſt ſee and read them, and other ſentences of holy Scriptures writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on the wals alſo for that purpoſe?</p>
            <p n="38">38 Item,
<note place="margin">Things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for diuine Seruice.</note> whether haue you a conuenient ſeat for your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to read ſeruice in, togither with a comely Pulpit ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent cloth or cuſhion for the ſame: a comely large Surplice, a faire Communion cup of gold, ſiluer, or other pure mettall, and a couer agréeable for the ſame, with all other things and ornaments neceſſaris for the celebration of Diuine Seruice, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments?</p>
            <p n="39">39 Item, whether are your Church or Chappels,
<note place="margin">Reparation of the Church, Parſonage-houſe, &amp;c.</note> with the Chancels thereof, and your Parſonages or Vicarage houſe, and all other houſing thereto belonging, in good reparations, and decent and comely kept, as well within as without, the ſeates well maintained, a ſure coffer with three locks &amp; keies for the ſafe keeping of your Rigiſter Booke, your Church-yards well ſenſed and kept without abuſe? if not, then through whoſe default, and what defects are therein?</p>
            <p n="40">40 Item, whether do you know,
<note place="margin">Gifts giuen to the vſe of the Church.</note> or haue heard of any lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by any mans wil, or any gift otherwiſe giuen to the poore, to the church, or to any other holy vſes, &amp; not performed or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed according to his will &amp; gift, and in whoſe handes the ſame doth now remaine?</p>
            <p n="41">41 Item, how many inhabitants within your pariſh,
<note place="margin">Recuſants.</note> men or women, aboue 16. yeares of age, be Popiſh Recuſants, or do refuſe to frequent Diuine Seruice eſtabliſhed by publike authoritie of this Realme, or to receiue the holy communion, what be their names, and of what degree, ſtate or trade of life are they? you are to preſent them all of both ſorts.</p>
            <p n="42">42 Item,
<note place="margin">How long they haue bin Recuſants.</note> how long the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants haue obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately abſtained either from Diuine Seruice, or from the Communion, as is aforeſaid: whether any long time, or one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince his Maieſties raigne?</p>
            <p n="43">
               <pb facs="tcp:25860:6"/> 43 Item,
<note place="margin">Whether the Miniſter ſeeks to reclaim the Recuſants.</note> whether is your Miniſter a Preacher ſufficiently qualified: and if he be, whether doth be from time to time after quiet and temperate conference to reclaime the Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants from their errors: and whether they or any of them doe refuſe ſuch conference with your Miniſter, or any other prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, who ſhall preſent vnto them his diligence in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalfe?</p>
            <p n="44">44 Item,
<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate perſons.</note> what perſons aforeſaid within your Pariſh, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the offence aforeſaid, or for any other contumacie or crime, doe remaine excommunicate, what be their names, and for what cauſe, &amp; how long they haue ſo ſtood excommunicate?</p>
            <p n="45">45 Item,
<note place="margin">Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens &amp; Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> whether were you the Church-wardens and Queſt-men choſen by the conſent of the Miniſter &amp; Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and whether haue the Church-wardens before you, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp a iuſt account for their time, and deliuered to you their ſucceſſors whatſoeuer money, or other things of right belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church, that was in their hands: and whether doe you, &amp; euery of you diligently ſee, that all the pariſhioners, do duely reſort to their Church euery Sunday and Holiday, and there continue the whole time of diuine Seruice, and none to walke or ſtand idle, or talking in the Church, or church-porch, or Church-yard, during that time: and whether do all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners and their families accordingly frequent their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, and there behaue themſelues ſoberly, attentiuely and decently, all the time of Diuine Seruice, yea or no? if no, then you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="46">46 Item,
<note place="margin">All reſort to Church, and receiue thrice a yeere.</note> whether doe all perſons aboue the age of ſixtéene yéeres vſually reſort to heare diuine Seruice vpon Sundaies and Holidayes appointed: and whether hath each one of your pariſhioners (being aboue the age of ſixtéene yeeres aforeſaid) receiued the holy Communion thrice this laſt yéere, &amp; chiefly once at Eaſter laſt, in your pariſh Church knéeling? if no, then you ſhall preſent their names which haue not ſo done.</p>
            <p n="47">47 Item,
<note place="margin">Pariſh Clarke.</note> whether haue you a fit pariſh Clark, aged twenty yéeres at leaſt, of honeſt conuerſation, and ſufficient for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and writing: and whether he be paid his wages without fraud, according to the moſt ancient cuſtome of your pariſh: if not, then by whom he is ſo defrauded and denied? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be choſen by the Parſon, or Vicar, or by whom?</p>
            <p n="48">48 Item,
<note place="margin">Table for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iages.</note> whether haue any in your pariſh béene married
<pb facs="tcp:25860:6"/>within the prohibited degrées, forbidden by the Law of God, and expreſſed in a certaine Table, publiſhed by authoritie in the yéere 1563. if yea, then ſhall you preſent their names, and whether haue you the ſaid Table publikely ſet vp in your Church, and faſtned to ſome conuenient place there?</p>
            <p n="49">49 Item, whether doth any heretofore diuorced,
<note place="margin">Perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorced.</note> keepe companie with any other at bed and at bord, what be their names, when and where were they married?</p>
            <p n="50">50 Item,
<note place="margin">To giue thankes after child-birth.</note> doth your Miniſter vſe the forme of thankſgiuing to women after childbirth: and whether hath he admitted any thereunto that was begotten with child in adultery, or forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, without licence of his Ordinarie? And whether haue any married wiues refuſed to come to church according to the Booke of Common Prayer, to giue God thankes after child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, in ſuch vſuall and decent manner, as anciently hath bin accuſtomed? if any be faultie herein, you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="51">51 Item, whether haue you any in your pariſh,
<note place="margin">Incontinent perſons, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, ſvvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp;c.</note> to your knowledge, or by common ſame and report, which haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted adulterie, fornication, or inceſt, which haue not beene publikely puniſhed to your knowledge: if yea, then with whom: or any man that hath attempted the chaſtitie of any woman, or hath ſollicited any woman, to the intent to haue the carnall knowledge of her bodie, or any in your Pariſh to bee Bawds, or receiuers of any ſuch perſons, or ſuſpected of any the crimes aforeſaid: are there any that are, or by common fame and report are reputed and taken to be ſuch perſons, or be commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drunkards, blaſphemers of Gods holy name, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon &amp; vſuall ſwearers, filthy ſpeakers, vſurers, ſymoniacall perſons, fighters, brawlers, or quarrellers in Church or Church-yard? you ſhall not faile to preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="52">52 Item,
<note place="margin">Harbouring incontinent perſons.</note> whether haue any in your pariſh receiued or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured any woman begotten with childe out of wedlock, and ſuffered them to depart againe without puniſhment firſt infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on them by their Ordinarie: you ſhall truely preſent as well the partie harbouring, as harboured, and who is ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be the Father of her childe?</p>
            <p n="53">53 Item,
<note place="margin">Wills.</note> whether are there in your Pariſh any Wils not yet prooued: you ſhall not faile to preſent the Executors, and
<pb facs="tcp:25860:7"/>all others <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="54">54 Item,
<note place="margin">Witches and ſuch like.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your Pariſhes, any witches, ſouthſayers, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ers, charmers, ſorcerers, or any that be ſuſpected for ſuch perſons: preſent their names, and what ſpeciall hurt they haue committed?</p>
            <p n="55">55 Item,
<note place="margin">Hoſpitals and Almeſ-houſes</note> whether there be any Hoſpitals or Almeſhouſes in your Pariſh, and whether the ſame be vſed, kept, &amp; ordered according to the foundations, lawes, and ſtatutes thereof, and in whom the fault is, that they are not ſo vſed and kept?</p>
            <p n="56">56 Item,
<note place="margin">Perambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate doth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually euery yéere in the Rogation weeke, gee with the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners in the perambulations about the Pariſh, according to the cuſtome and vſe of ancient time, and doth ſay the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſuffrages appointed for the ſame?</p>
            <p n="57">57 Item,
<note place="margin">Fift of Auguſt to be kept Holy-day.</note> whether is the fift day of Auguſt (being the day of the Kings Maieſties moſt happy deliuerance from the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and bloudie attempt of the Earle <hi>Gowry</hi> and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with their adherents) obſerued and kept feſtiuall within your pariſh, with prayer and thankſgiuing, and with ceſſation from labor, as by publike authoritie it is appointed: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue you in your pariſh the booke publiſhed by authority, which containeth the forme of prayer, with thankſgiuing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that day: and whether is the fift day of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber obſerued and kept feſtiuall,
<note place="margin">Gun-povvder Treaſon. Nouemb. 5. Any thing elſe.</note> as by a ſpeciall act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that caſe prouided, is appointed?</p>
            <p n="58">58 Doe you know of any other matter of Eccleſiaſticall cognizance worthy the preſentment in your iudgement, which you hold fit to be reformed? if you do, you ſhall like wiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame by vertue of your Oathes aforeſaid.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25860:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
